“97 percent of climate scientists agree
that climate change is real.”
How many times have you heard that statement?
Probably hundreds. It may seem like a compelling
and scientific argument against fossil fuels,
but it’s one of the most illogical, unscientific
arguments you can make. To see how, let’s
use this form of argument
for another controversial product, vaccines.
says, “97 percent of doctors
What would you say in response?
You’d probably say, “Yeah but the benefits
far outweigh the side effects.”
By saying that “97% of doctors agree that
vaccine side effects are real” without mentioning
any of the benefits of vaccines, the anti-vaccine
activist is trying to get you to look at the
potential dangers of vaccines out of context.
When fossil fuel opponents say “97 percent
of climate scientists agree that climate change
is real,” they are doing the same. Yes,
using fossil fuels for energy has a side effect—increasing
the amount of CO2 in the atmosphere. Okay.
But what about the upside? In the case of
fossil fuel that upside is enormous: the cheap,
plentiful, and reliable energy that makes
modern life possible, and at a scale no other
energy source can match.
So, how significant is the side effect? This
raises another problem with the statement
“97% percent of climate scientists agree
that climate change is real.” It tells us
nothing about the meaning or magnitude of
“climate change”—whether it’s a mild,
manageable warming or a runaway, catastrophic
warming. This is an example of the fallacy
of equivocation—using the same term in different,
contradictory ways.
If someone were to say “97% of doctors agree
that vaccine side effects are real,”
what exact “vaccine side effects” do the doctors
agree on? That a certain number of babies
will get a rash? Or that large percentages
will get full-blown autism? Precision is key, right?
But fossil fuel opponents don’t want you
to know the precise magnitude of climate change.
Because if you did you wouldn’t be scared
of climate change,
you would be scared of losing the benefits of fossil fuels.
For example, listen to how Secretary of State John Kerry manipulates the “97 percent of scientists” line.
“97 percent of climate
scientists have confirmed that climate change
is happening and that human activity is responsible,”
he said in a speech in Indonesia in 2014.
Later, in the same speech, he claimed that
Scientists agree that, “The world as we
know it will change—and it will change dramatically
for the worse.” 97 percent of climate scientists
never said any such thing.
So what did the 97 percent actually say? It
turns out, nothing remotely resembling catastrophic
climate change. One of the main studies justifying
97 percent was done by John Cook, a climate
communications fellow for the Global Change
Institute in Australia. Here’s his own summary
of his survey: “Cook et al. found
that over 97 percent [of papers surveyed]
endorsed the view that the Earth is warming
up and human emissions of greenhouse gases
are the main cause.”
“Main cause” means “over 50 percent.
But the vast majority of papers don’t say
that human beings are the main cause of recent
warming. In fact, one analysis showed
that less than 2 percent of papers actually said that.
How did Cook get to 97 percent, then? First,
he added papers that explicitly said there
was man-made warming but didn’t say how
much. Then, he added papers that didn’t
even say there was man-made warming, but he
thought it was implied.
A scientific researcher has a sacred obligation
to accurately report his findings.
Cook and researchers like him have failed us—as have
the politicians and media figures who have
blindly repeated the 97 percent claim to support
their anti-fossil fuel goals.
How can we protect ourselves against this
kind of manipulation? Whenever someone tells
you that scientists agree on something, ask
two questions: “What exactly do they agree on?
And, “How did they prove it?”
I’m Alex Epstein, author of The Moral Case
for Fossil Fuels, for Prager University.